Finding aid to Record Group 9. Photographs, of the YWCA of the U.S.A. records SSC.MS.00324.RG9
Sophia Smith Collection
- Prints and negatives, 1
  - Program, E
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 8)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA housing and recreation facilities and programs for women working in war work during World War I. Several photographs depicts women participating in military drills as part of YWCA war work clubs, and include images of Miss. Alice Winters presenting a rifle to Secretary of the Navy Josephus Daniels.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Industrial housing; Industrial recreation; Drill and minor tactics; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, Connecticut, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 9)
      Photographs of YWCA recreation and club programs for industrial women employed during World War I. Photographed activities include images of women enjoying camps and outdoor recreation as well as group photographs and portraits of members.
      Bridgeport, Fairfield, Connecticut, United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Industrial recreation; Swimming; Women -- Employment
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, New Jersey (Box 1037, Folder 10-11)
      Photographs of industrial housing and recreation programs at Players' House in Camp Dix, and the Industrial War Service Center in Bloomfield, New Jersey. Players' House provided housing and home-like accommodations for actresses. The Industrial War Service Center in Bloomfield served women employed in nearby industry during the war providing leisure and food service as part of their program.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Industrial recreation; Actresses; Industrial housing; New Jersey, United States
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, New York, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 12-15)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA housing and recreation programs for women war workers in New York including cafeterias, leisure activities, a club for nurses, social events, and a separate club for African American war workers and military.
      New York war work housing and recreation photographs are arranged as follows:
      Industrial club house and cafeteria, Bush Terminal, Brooklyn
      Recreation for nurses, New York City and Camp Mills
      Central Branch and West Side Branch, New York City
      War service and recreation center for African American women, 127 West 136th St.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Women -- Employment; Nurses; Industrial recreation; Industrial housing; African American women -- Societies and clubs; New York, United States
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, Texas, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 16)
      Photographs of industrial girls, club rooms and centers for women employed during World War I in Texas. Identified photographs include centers in Waco and Houston.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Women -- Employment; Industrial recreation; Texas, United States
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, Virginia, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 17)
      Photographs of industrial recreation programs as well as interior and exterior shots of housing and facilities. Identified photographs indicate the facilities are at the Penniman Plant in Virginia.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Industrial recreation; Industrial housing; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Virginia, United States
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, Washington, D.C., circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 18)
      Photographs of the YWCA country club in Washington, D.C.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Industrial recreation; Washington, District of Columbia, United States
    - World War I: International work, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 19)
      Identified and unidentified photographs of the international work of the YWCA of the USA during World War I as well as photographs of local scenes and a first aid class.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work
    - World War I: International work, overseas staff, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 20)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA staff serving overseas during World War I mainly comprised of posed and candid group photographs. Most photographs are identified with a location and many identify the women in the photograph.
    - World War I: International work, France, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 21-22)
      Photographs of the work of the YWCA of the USA in France during World War I including foyers, hostess houses, mobil unites, recreation programs, housing, and programs for French war workers.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- France; Industrial recreation; Industrial housing; Women -- Employment -- France; France
    - World War I: International work, Poland, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 1-2)
      Photographs of the work of the YWCA of the USA in Poland during and after World War I including the work of the Polish Grey Samaritans and work with refugees and orphans. Polish Grey Samaritain, trained under the YWCA of the USA were women of Polish background trained to provide relief work in Poland immediately following the war. Photographs include images of their work in Poland as well as some photographs identified as New York City.
      Photographs of international work in Poland are arranged as follows:
      Polish Grey Samaritains
      Refugee work
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- Poland; World War, 1914-1918 -- Refugees; Refugees -- Poland; Refugee children; Poland
    - World War I: International work, Training School for Old Country Service, circa 1919 (Box 1038, Folder 3)
      Photographs of women wearing traditional dress as part of an international garden party and additional photographs from the Training School for Old Country Service.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Traditional dress; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Women immigrants
    - World War I: Women war workers, general and miscellaneous, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 4)
      Photographs highlighting women's employment during World War I including employment in jobs previously unavailable to women. Photographs included women in factory jobs, postal work, service, typewriter repair, and shoe repair. Also included is a photograph of an integrated laundry. The caption credits teh YWCA and was used in a Smithsonian exhibit.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers
    - World War I: Women war workers, construction, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 5)
      Photographs of women working in the construction and building trades during World War I.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers; Women construction workers
    - World War I: Women war workers, Erie Railroad, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 6)
      Photographs of women railroad workers on the Erie Railroad during World War I.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers; Women railroad employees
    - World War I: Women war workers, mill work and factories, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 7)
      Photographs of women working in mills and factories during World War I.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers
    - World War I: Women war workers, motion picture operator, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 8)
      Photographs of women working and training as projectionists and motion picture operators. One photographs credits the woman as the "first girl motion picture operator."
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers; Women in the motion picture industry
    - World War I: Women war workers, packaging, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 9)
      Photographs of women working in canning and packaging during World War I.
    - World War I: Women war workers, munitions and steel, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 10)
      Photographs of women working in the munitions and steel industries in Detroit, Michigan during World War I.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Detroit, Wayne, Michigan, United States; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers
    - World War I: Women war workers, New Jersey, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 11-12)
      Photographs of women war workers at Internatioanl Fuse and Arms Company in Bloomfield, and Newark shipyards.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers; New Jersey, United States
    - World War I: Women war workers, New York, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 13-15)
      Photographs of women war workers in transportation in New York including images of women mechanics, drivers, and railroad workers.
      New York women war workers photographs are arranged as follows:
      Brooklyn Rapid Transit
      Bush Terminal, Brooklyn
      Transportation, New York City
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers; Women railroad employees; New York, United States
    - World War I: Women war workers: Pennsylvania Navy Yard, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 16)
      Photographs of women working at the Philadelphia Naval yard in Pennsylvania.
      Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers
    - World War I: Women war workers, Virginia cotton mills, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 17)
      Photographs of women working in cotton mills in Lynchburg, Virginia during World War I.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Women -- Employment; Cotton manufacture; Lynchburg, Campbell, Virginia, United States
    - World War I: Women war workers, France, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 18)
      Photographs of women employed in war work in France during World War I.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- France; Women -- Employment; France; Women -- Employment -- France; Women blue collar workers
    - World War I: Women war workers, Great Britain, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 19)
      Photographs of women employed in war work in Great Britain during World War I.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Women -- Employment; United Kingdom; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women -- Great Britain; Women blue collar workers
    - World War I: Anna C. Ladd artificial faces for disfigured veterans, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1038, Folder 20)
      Photographs of soldiers before and after the application of Anna C. Ladd's facial reconstruction masks.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Masks; War wounds; Ladd, Anna Coleman, 1878-1939
    - Women working, Great Britain press photographs (Box 1050, Folder 4)
    - World War II: Japanese Evacuee Project and internment, circa 1941-1946; 1989 (Box 1038, Folder 21)
      Photographs from Japanese American internment camps in the United States during World War II. Identified photographs identify Manzanar in particular. The YWCA of the USA extended service into the internment camps and photographs include images of YWCA clubs, Girl Reserve and "Forget-me-not" clubs, YWCA conferences, and student groups in addition to images of children and families with personal belongings waiting to be transported, daily life, and facilities. Also included are several photographs of a 1989 site visit identified as Phoenix, Arizona.
      Japanese Americans; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1939-1945 -- Japanese Americans; Concentration camps; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. G.R. Dept.
    - World War II: International work, circa 1939-1946 (Box 1038, Folder 22)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA workers abroad during and after World War II.
      World War, 1939-1945 -- Women; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1939-1945--War work
    - World War II: International, YWCA war service centers, 1943-1947 (Box 1038, Folder 23)
      Photographs of YWCA war service centers during World War II. The centers served civilian and military women working and stationed abroad.
      World War, 1939-1945 -- Women; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; Women soldiers
    - World War II: International, War relief work, circa 1944-1945 (Box 1038, Folder 24)
      Photographs highlighting the international relief work of the YWCA of the USA during and following World War II.
      Reconstruction (1939-1951); World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; War relief workers; War relief
    - World War II: International, Great Britain, circa 1939-1946 (Box 1039, Folder 1-3)
      Photographs of YWCA programs and facilities in Great Britain during World War II. The YWCA of Great Britain, a "beneficiary of the World Emergency Fund of the YWCA of the USA," had programs for women in the military, women conducting relief work, and generally for women in Great Britain affected by the war. Photographs include mobil units, YWCA club programs,relief work, and visits from Mrs. Churchill, Queen Elizabeth, and Princess Elizabeth.
      World War II international work in Great Britain photographs are arranged as follows:
      Hotel Victoria Series
      The Palace Hut, Salisbury
      World War, 1939-1945 -- Women; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Women soldiers; Soldiers -- Recreation; World War, 1939-1945--War work; United Kingdom; YWCA of GB; Elizabeth II, Queen of Great Britain, 1926-; Elizabeth, Queen, consort of George VI, King of Great Britain, 1900-2002; Churchill, Clementine, 1885-1977
    - United Community Defense Services, 1954; undated (Box 1039, Folder 4)
      Photographs of YWCA United Community Defense Services staff and programs.
      Rural development; Community education; YWCA of the U.S.A.. UCDS
    - United Community Defense Services: San Diego, California (Box 1039, Folder 5)
      Photographs of YWCA United Community Defense Services programs and activities for "defense workers and their families." Photographed programs and activities include hobby nights, open houses, social dance, music, sewing, board games and other recreation and leisure activities.
      Recreation; San Diego, San Diego, California, United States; Defense industries -- Employees; YWCA of the U.S.A.. UCDS
    - United Community Defense Services: Savannah River Site (Box 1039, Folder 6)
      Photographs of programs and activities of the YWCA United Community Degese Services serving the Savannah River Site workers and their families.
      Defense industries -- Employees; Recreation; Nuclear industry; Mobile home living; Georgia, United States; South Carolina, United States; United States. Department of Energy. Savannah River Site
    - United Community Defense Services: Portsmouth Gaseous Diffusion Plant, circa 1952-1955 (Box 1039, Folder 7-8)
      Photographs of YWCA United Community Defense Services programs and facilitites for the families Portsmouth Gaseous Diffusion Plant area. Photographs include images of YWCA trailers and the activities they facilitate in addition to photographs of the mobile home communities and dailiy life.
      Defense industries -- Employees; Recreation; Mobile home living; Nuclear industry; Portsmouth Gaseous Diffusion Plant; YWCA of the U.S.A.. UCDS
    - United Service Organizations, circa 1941-1973 (Box 1039, Folder 9-10)
      Photographs of United Service Organization (USO) staff and activities in the United States. Some photographs are identified as YWCA members or clubs and others are unidentified.
      Soldiers -- Recreation; Women soldiers; Families of military personnel; United Service Organizations (U.S.)
    - United Service Organizations: YWCA USO Division, circa 1946-1970 (Box 1039, Folder 11)
      Photographs of leaders and staff of the YWCA of the USA USO Division, and leaders and staff of the United Service Organization (USO) including photographs of YWCA of the USA USO Division representatives receiving awards and citations.
      Special events; Awards; Leadership in women; YWCA of the U.S.A.. National Board. USO Division; United Service Organizations (U.S.)
    - United Service Organizations: YWCA USO Division anniversary, 1966 (Box 1039, Folder 12)
      Photographs of special events celebrating the twenty fifth anniversary of the YWCA of the USA USO Division.
      Special events; Leadership in women; YWCA of the U.S.A.. National Board. USO Division -- Anniversaries, etc.; United Service Organizations (U.S.)
    - United Service Organizations: Clubs, circa 1944-1967 (Box 1039, Folder 13-16)
      Photographs of United Service Organization (USO) clubs in the United States and Vietnam. Photographs include images of programs and activities, anniversary celebrations, dedication ceremonies, and groundbreakings. Some photographs are specified as YWCA USO clubs and other are not identified.
      United Service Organization club photographs are arranged as follows:
      Anniversaries
      Openings
      Special events; Soldiers -- Recreation; YWCA of the U.S.A.. National Board. USO Division; United Service Organizations (U.S.)
    - United Service Organizations: Staff, circa 1944-1969 (Box 1039, Folder 17-18)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA USO Division leaders and staff as well as United Service Organization (USO) staff and leaders.
      Leadership in women; YWCA of the U.S.A.. National Board. USO Division -- Employees; United Service Organizations (U.S.) -- Employees
    - United Service Organizations: Staff conferences, 1952-1969 (Box 1039, Folder 19)
      Group photographs from area and national United Service Organization (USO) staff conferences.
      Leadership in women; Congresses and conventions; YWCA of the U.S.A.. National Board. USO Division -- Employees; United Service Organizations (U.S.) -- Employees
  - Student Work, F
    - General and miscellaneous, circa 1910-1989 (Box 1040, Folder 1-3)
      Photographs of leaders, students, programs, conferences and other activities with college students in the YWCA of the USA and its student associations.
      Student movements; Women college students; National Student YWCA
    - Alumnae network, 1984 (Box 1040, Folder 4)
      Photographs of National Student YWCA members and alums at alumae events.
      Women college students; National Student YWCA
    - Conferences: Asilomar/Pacific Coast, 1900; 1920 (Box 1040, Folder 5)
      Group photographs from YWCA student conferences in California.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; California, United States; Asilomar Conference Grounds (Pacific Grove, Calif.); National Student YWCA
    - Conferences: Geneva/Mid-West/Central, circa 1872-1959 (Box 1040, Folder 6-11)
      Photographs from student YWCA conferences in the Central region, often referred to as the Geneva region, roughly covering midwestern states. Many conferences were held at the Lake Geneva camp and conferences grounds and photographs include images of students participating in camp activities such as lakeside recreation, hikes, pageants, and swimming in addition to posed group photographs. Later conferences were often co-ed and included delegates from student YMCA associations.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; Student movements; Camps; Outdoor recreation; Midwest, United States; National Student YWCA; Student Young Men's Christian Association
    - Conferences: Middle Atlantic/Eagles Mere/East Central, 1911-1918 (Box 1040, Folder 12)
      Group photographs from the east central regional student YWCA conferences held at Eagles Mere, Pennsylvania.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; Eagles Mere, Sullivan, Pennsylvania, United States; National Student YWCA
    - Conferences: New England/Maqua, 1920-1921 (Box 1040, Folder 13)
      Group photographs from the 1920 and 1921 New England regional conference of the student YWCA held at Camp Maqua, Poland, Maine.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; New England, United States; Poland, Androscoggin, Maine, United States; National Student YWCA
    - Conferences: Pacific Northwest/Seabeck, 1913-1957 (Box 1040, Folder 14)
      Photographs of the Pacific Northwest regional conferences of student YWCA's. Conferences were often held at camp groups and conference grounds and identified camps include Seabeck. Photographs include posed and candid group and individual portraits as well as photographs of camp activities and outdoor recreation. Later conferences appear to be co-ed, likely with student YMCA's.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; Outdoor recreation; Camps; Northwestern United States, United States; National Student YWCA; Student Young Men's Christian Association
    - Conferences: Rocky Mountain/Western, circa 1906-1920 (Box 1040, Folder 15)
      Photographs from the western, sometimes called Rocky Mountain, regional conferences of student YWCA's, held at Estes Park, Colorado, Chautauqua Park, Iowa, and Cascade, Colorado.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; Western United States, United States; National Student YWCA
    - Conferences: Silver Bay/Eastern/Northeast, 1914-1917 (Box 1040, Folder 16)
      Photographs from eastern regional conferences of student YWCA's held at Silver Bay.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; Outdoor recreation; Camps; Eastern United States, United States; National Student YWCA
    - Conferences: Southern, circa 1898-1953 (Box 1040, Folder 17-18)
      Photographs from southern regional conferences of student YWCA associations. Photographs appear to include images from African American southern student conferences, likely segregated from the white student conferences. One photograph identifies itself as "probably the earliest photograph of an all-Black group in the National Board Archives." dating the photographs between 1910 and 1914.
      Women college students; Congresses and conventions; African American women college students; National Student YWCA
    - Conferences: Unidentified and miscellaneous, circa 1930-1939; 1969; undated (Box 1040, Folder 19)
      Photographs from unidentified student YWCA conferences.